NWLB Southern Coal Procedures Records 5313
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NWLB Southern Coal Procedures Records
1943
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945)
5313
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Records of the U.S. National War Labor Board in the matter of the Operators Negotiating Committee, Appalachin Joint Conference, Southern Appalachin Joint Wage Conference and the United Mineworkers of America.
5596296
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 18, 2005
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Fact Finding Panel was appointed by the National War Labor Board to investigate the dispute which arose when the parties were unable to agree on the terms of a new contract in the spring of 1943. The following were members of the panel: Morris L. Cooke, representing the public, chairman; David B. Robertson, representing labor; and Walter White, representing industry.
Negotiations began on March 10, 1943. The principal demands of the United Mine Workers were: a wage increase of $2 a day, payment for travel time from portal to portal for all underground workers, inclusion of some supervisory personnel, and several minor issues.
No agreement could be reached, and the case was certified to the War Labor Board on April 22, 1943. The panel held its first hearing in Washington D.C. on April 28 at which the Mine Workers refused to appear. The panel was recessed when it learned that the Mine Workers had gone on strike in violation of the no-strike agreement of 1941. On May 1 the Federal Government seized the mines and the miners went back to work. On May 6, the National War Labor Board resumed hearings and issued a report on May 25, which the Mine Workers refused to accept, and struck again. President Roosevelt ordered the miners back to work. On June 7 negotiations for a new contract were resumed and in mid-June the Central Pennsylvania signed an agreement which it later repudiated on pressure from the other operators. On July 21 the Illinois operation signed an agreement which the NWLB refused to approve because it violated the "Little Steel Formula." The mines were returned to the operators on October 1. The miners struck for a third time on November 1, and the mines were again seized by the government, and a contract between the government and the Mine Workers was signed on November 3.
Scope and Contents
Records of the U.S. National War Labor Board in the matter of the Operators Negotiating Committee, Appalachin Joint Conference, Southern Appalachin Joint Wage Conference and the United Mineworkers of America.
Included are hearing proceedings, reports, and statements of the parties in the dispute.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5241: National Wartime Conference of the Professions, the Sciences, the Arts and the White Collar Fields 5289: AoM Records 5309: NWLB Files 5310: NWLB Records 5311: NWLB Region II Office Files and Cases 5312: NWLB Files 5314: NWLB Non-Ferrous Metals Commission Records 5699: William Bardsley Collection of United States National Recovery Administrations and National War Labor Board Printed and Mimeographed Documents 5752 mf: Papers of the National War Labor Board on Microfilm 5780/085: ILGWU National War Labor Board case files 6127m: National War Labor Board Executive Meeting Transcript
Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Miners -- Labor unions -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Mining industry -- United States; United States. National Labor Relations Board (1942-1945); Southern Coal Producers; United Mineworkers of America
5596296
- National War Labor Board Panel Hearing, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  April 28th; in the case of the Operators Negotiating Committee, Appalachian Joint Conference, and the Southern Appalachian Joint Wage Conference and the United Mine Workers of America, 1 vol.
- National War Labor Board Fact Finding Panel, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Hearing with same parties, May 6-11, 1943, 4 volumes, 624 pp.
- Public Hearing before the National War Labor Board, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  June 10th; in the Case of the Bituminous Coal Operators and the United Mine Workers of America, 1 volume, 152 pp.
- Public Hearing before the National War Labor Board, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Aug. 3rd; in the case of the Illinois Coal Operators Association and the limited Mine Workers of America, District 12, 1 volume, 90 pp.
- Public Hearing before the National War Labor Board, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Oct 21st-23rd; in the case of the Illinois Coal Operators Association and the limited Mine Workers of America, District 12, 3 volumes.
- Statistical Data and exhibits (Box 1, Folder 6)
  5 volumes, 280 pp.
- National Coal Industry on the Bituminous Coal Industry, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Statement of Facts of the Operators Negotiating Committee, Southern Appalachian Joint Wage Conference, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Southern Coal Producers Association on the Bituminous Coal Industry (Box 2, Folder 3)
- National War Labor Board, Division of wage stabilization (Box 2, Folder 4)
  on wages and related problems in the Bituminous Coal Industry
- Statement of David Friday (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Economic Evidence bearing on the demand of the Bituminous Coal Workers for a General Wage Increase.